Brown, G.M. mss., 1982-1988 LMC 1139
Lilly Library
Brown, G.M. mss.
1982-1988
Lilly Library
Brown, George Mackey, 1921-
LMC 1139
1 Box 1 standard
The Brown, G.M., mss., 1982-1988, consist of a selection of stories by Scottish poet and author George Mackay Brown, 1921-. The selection was to be published by John Murray in Fall 1989.
Access Restrictions
This collection is open for research.
Many collections are housed offsite; retrieval requires advance notice. Please make an appointment a minimum of one week in advance of your visit.
Biogrpahical Note
The Brown, G.M., mss., 1982-1988 contains short stories by Scottish poet and author George Mackay Brown (1921-1996) that were later published by John Murray in Fall 1989. Brown was born in Stromness, a town in the Orkney. During his childhood, he experienced poverty, depression, and eventually tuberculosis that kept him from entering the army during World War II. As an alternative, he began writing in 1944 for The Orkney Herald and developed a journalistic career. In the 1950s, Brown became a student at NewBattle Abbey College under poet Edwin Muir. He then began to publish several poems, including his first volume The Storm, in the mid-to-late 1950s. After subsequently studying English at the University of Edinburgh, his poems began to acquire more notice. Along with poetry collections like Loaves and Fishes (1959), he also wrote short story volumes like Hawkfall (1974) and The Sea-King's Daughter (1991), as well as a few plays, several novels, and children's story collections.
Scope and Content Note
The Brown, G.M., mss., 1982-1988, consist of a selection of stories by Scottish poet and author George Mackay Brown, 1921-. The selection is to be published by John Murray in Fall 1989.
The stories present are titled: Anna's Boy, A Christmas Story; Bessie Millie's Wind Shop: A Play; Captain Bligh and Two Midshipmen; A Child's Christmas in Orkney; The Corn and the Tares; A Croft in January; Dialogue at the Year's End; Dancey; The Eve of St. Thomas; A Game of Chess; The Hooded Ones; The Last Island Boy; The Nativity Bell and the Falconer; One Christmas in Birsay; The Sea King's Daughter; The Silent Girl from Shetland; The Stone Rose; The Tree and the Harp; The Weaver; and The White Horse Inn.
Acquisition Information
Purchase: 1989
Brown, George Mackey, 1921-
- Two poems for Kenna, 1988-02-27 (Box 1)
- Anna's Boy (Christmas Story), 1985-10 (Box 1)
- Bessie Millie's Wind Shop: A Play, 1982-04 (Box 1)
- Captain Bligh and Two Midshipmen, 1985-10 (Box 1)
- A Child's Christmas in Orkney, (undated) (Box 1)
- The Corn and the Tares, (undated) (Box 1)
- A Croft in January, 1988 (Box 1)
- Dancey, 1986-01 (Box 1)
- Dialogue at the Year's End, 1986-11 (Box 1)
- The Eve of St. Thomas, 1986-10 (Box 1)
- A Game of Chess f.1, 1985-11 (Box 1)
- A Game of Chess f.2, 1985-11 (Box 1)
- The Hooded Ones, 1986-11 (Box 1)
- The Last Island Boy, 1985-10 (Box 1)
- The Nativity Bell and the Falconer, 1987-11 (Box 1)
- One Christmas in Birsay, 1987-11 (Box 1)
- The Sea King's Daughter, 1988-01 (Box 1)
- The Silent Girl from Shetland, 1986-11 (Box 1)
- The Stone Rose, 1984-12 (Box 1)
- The Tree and the Harp, 1986-03 (Box 1)
- The Weaver, 1987-11 (Box 1)
- The White Horse Inn, 1987-08 (Box 1)